Okay,
we're doing סנהדרין דף קי, Sanhedrin Daf Kuf Yud, we're going to
pick up at
a
little bit
before the two dots on קט עמוד ב. Kuf Tet Amud Bet.
I think we got up to, where did we get up to
yesterday? תנו רבנן עדת קורח אין להם חלק לעולם הבא. Tanu Rabbanan
Adat Korach ein lahem chelek le'olam haba. Yes? Okay, so
we'll start to translate the word of עדה, edah, but like, you
know, followers basically, you know, how do you say it, by followers?
Like a lot of people were sort of drawn in by that
but like, you know, the immediate people like 250 people, you know,
however many people it was. So this group
there, her, yeah, whatever that means. You know, his group, his followers,
אין להם חלק לעולם הבא. ein lahem chelek le'olam haba. So they
don't have a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek le'olam haba, שנאמר ותכס עליהם
הארץ. shenemar vatechas aleihem ha'aretz. So when it describes their demise, you
know, when the ground opens them up, so ותכס עליהם הארץ, vatechas
aleihem ha'aretz, so the ground opened up and swallowed
them, ויאבדו מתוך הקהל. vayovdu mitoch hakahal. So the first part, ותכס
עליהם הארץ, vatechas aleihem ha'aretz, is בעולם הזה, ba'olam hazeh, ויאבדו מתוך
הקהל, vayovdu mitoch hakahal, and then they were lost from the congregation,
the rest of the Jewish
people, זה עולם הבא. zeh olam haba. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi
Akiva. רבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer, הרי
הן כאבידה המתבקשת. harei hen ke'aveidah hamitbakeshet.
It's like something that's lost, you know, but the, like, the owner
kind of wants to find it again, right? So
sort of, I guess like what that means is, you know, meaning
like their souls were sort of lost, their bodies were lost, but
God kind of wants to find them again, you know, or whoever
it is that wants to find them again,
I would think that's kind of referring to השם. Hashem.
But so like שנאמר תעיתי כשה אובד בקש עבדך כי מצותיך לא
שכחתי. shenemar ta'iti kaseh oved bakesh avdecha ki mitzotecha lo shachachti. So
I have, this is a פסוק pasuk from תהילים, Tehillim, so תעיתי,
ta'iti, I've gone astray, כשה אובד, kaseh oved, like a wandering sheep,
בקש עבדך, bakesh avdecha, please,
like בקש bakesh is like that's the tie, like כאבידה המתבקשת, ke'aveidah
hamitbakeshet, like search, seek, I think it's used in this, not just
to ask. Sometimes בקשה bakesha can mean, you know, ask, but here
I think it's more like
seek.
So seek your servant כי מצותיך לא שכחתי ki mitzotecha lo shachachti
because I did not forget your mitzvot, which is very interesting, right?
That
I didn't forget your מצווה, mitzvah, right? So I mean, you know,
as opposed to all the other kings that we were learning before
were clearly seen, you know, it is, they really did lots of
bad עבירות, aveirot, like עבודה זרה avodah zarah and stuff like that.
You know, here doesn't, I mean we have no indication that עדת
קורח Adat Korach weren't keeping the rest of the מצוות, mitzvot, but
they're, you know, arguing over what they're arguing, right? So they may
still have been keeping the other מצוות, mitzvot, so you know, maybe
that sort
of,
and it's hard to understand, you know, why. Look,
they weren't, they weren't like מסית ומדיח mesit umadiach other people from
following the rest of the מצוות, mitzvot, right? You know, at the
end of the day, but you know, very drastic measures were taken
though because you don't want to have a rebellion continue.
So you know, maybe I guess in some sort of afterlife,
when these accounts are settled, but God's point has already been made,
you know, they don't have to be permanently cut off from עולם
הבא. olam haba. So that may be why, you know, God could
at some point can be seeking them. You know, right now they're
still lost, right? You know, but maybe at some future point they
can kind of be found again. I think that's kind of the
way to.
בקשה Bakesha request also?
Yeah. So it's the same root, right? בקש, bakesh, you
seek?
The request is maybe because you're seeking an answer. Oh, okay, good.
I think it comes more from that, that's what I would say.
But you know, I'm not a linguist. So anyway, so that's, so
it's a very nice way of framing it. Okay, ויקח קורח, vayikach
Korach,
now that we're talking about עדת קורח, adat Korach, let's analyze the
whole story of קורח. Korach. So which is a very strange way,
as we all know, of
beginning
a פרשה, parsha, ויקח קורח, vayikach Korach, he took, what did he
take? ויקח קורח בן יצהר בן קהת בן לוי ודתן ואבירם בני
אליאב ואון בן פלת בני ראובן, vayikach Korach ben Yitzhar ben Kehat
ben Levi vedatan ve'aviram bnei eliav ve'on ben pelet bnei reuven, that's
the rest of the פסוק, pasuk, son of Yitzhar, son of Kehat,
son of Levi, and Dathan and Abiram, sons of Eliab and On
son of Pelet, sons of Reuben. So all those people, but then
it doesn't say what he took, right? Because then the next פסוק
pasuk begins with another verb, ויקומו לפני משה ואנשים מבני ישראל חמישים
ומאתיים. vayukumu lifnei moshe ve'anashim mibnei yisrael chamishim umatayim. So they all
got up in front of משה Moshe and then these 250 people,
נשיאי עדה קריאי מועד אנשי שם. nesiei edah kriei moed anshei shem.
So all those people got up. So what is Korach taking? So
you know, so ויקח קורח, vayikach Korach, like he kind of mean
like he gathered these people together, you know, he gathered whoever it
was, but then, you know, other words for that like ויאסף vayasof
or ויאספו. vayasfu.
So or he took himself to, you know, he took himself, he
got himself together to
rebel
against משה. Moshe. That's really you know what it, the פשט pshat
of the פסוק pasuk is, but it's still a strange way of
saying it. So the גמרא Gemara picking up on that says, שלקח
מקח רע לעצמו. shelekach mekach ra le'atzmo. So he sort of like,
you know, took bad advice for himself, like מקח mekach literally is
a purchase, but you know, he sort of like is, the idea
is really more to say מקח רע, mekach ra, like you know,
he took a bad, like a bad bunch
of. So now, it's very interesting like you know how the גמרא
Gemara דרשנס darshens names. It can go either way with this, usually
we don't see it going as you'll see the way it's going
to go now.
So it darshens names:
קורח Korach
what do we darshen on that? שנעשה קורחה בישראל she'na'asa korcha be'Yisrael
so like, you know, like a קורחה korcha is like a bald
spot. So like, you know, so the, so this, the place where
these people should have been is now, you know, no longer there.
So he sort of balded Israel. בן יצהר Ben Yitzhar we don't
usually have any problems with his ancestors, but now we're going to
darshen it in this way: בן יצהר בן שהרתיח עליו את כל
העולם כצהריים. Ben Yitzhar ben she'hirtiach alav et kol ha'olam ke'tzohorayim. So
you see the words יצהר, Yitzhar, הרתיח, hirtiach, and צהריים. tzohorayim. So
להרתיח lehartiach is to like, you know, boil up
to or, you know, the way they translate here is excited. But,
so anyway, so he did that, את כל העולם, et kol ha'olam,
you know, the entire world against himself like צהריים, tzohorayim, you know,
like... להרתיח lehartiach I think works better with the boiling metaphor. I
think of a boiling pot and like צהריים tzohorayim is like the
heat of the day. So, you know, he ended up getting if
you will like singed, you know, if you want to keep the
metaphor of fire here. בן קהת Ben Kehat
so בן שהקהה שיני מולידיו.
ben she'hikka
shinei molidav. He sort of like blunted the teeth or weakened the
teeth
of those that, you know, his ancestors, his forebears. בן לוי Ben
Levi מי שנעשה לוייה לגיהנום. mi she'na'asa levaya le'Gehennom. Right, we don't
want to say something too bad about לוי Levi himself, right, because
sometimes we do that, right, we darshen: oh yeah, you know, someone's
bad, the ancestors are bad. We have a lot of that, but
we obviously don't want to say that about יצהר, Yitzhar, קהת, Kehat,
and לוי, Levi, but we want to darshen it, so that's why
I'm saying it's a very interesting way to go about it over
here. Usually, like, you know, don't touch
the יחסנים, yichasnim, right? We're already going up to
לוי. Levi. לוי שנעשה לוייה לגיהנום. Levi she'na'asa levaya le'Gehennom. So he
had an entourage going with him to גיהנום, Gehennom, meaning him and
his followers. Not לוי Levi himself, but, you know,
the people that קורח Korach was with.
So he's darshening the ancestors' names but to be about קורח?
Korach? Yeah, I know, we don't usually do that. That's what I'm
saying, usually we darshen the ancestors' names about themselves like, oh, someone's
bad, he was bad, he comes from bad stock, and so on.
שלומית בת דברי, Shelomit bat Divri, right? We have that later,
like in... כאושא דדברנית, ke'usha de'davranit, right? You know, like, oh she
was always chattering, not in a bad way. We have this plenty
of times, we see this all the time, right? But I said
over here we don't want to touch these people, but so I
said we darshen it but not about them, but about, you know,
as we were just pointing out. So, but we don't usually do
that, you know what I mean? We could have just left it,
but we don't pass up the opportunity to give a
דרשה. derasha. ובחשבונא נמי בן יעקב, uve'cheshbona nami ben Yaakov, already going
back that far,
already going back, you know, three generations from קורח, Korach, so why
not go back further? ובחשבונא נמי בן יעקב. uve'cheshbona nami ben Yaakov.
You know, if we're already darshening, we can be creative.
בן שעיקב עצמו לגיהנום.
ben she'ikkeiv atzmo le'Gehennom. Right? He sort of, as in עקב. akeiv.
Not like, you know, you can say עכבה akava with a delay,
that'd be with a כ, kaf, but this is עקב akeiv as
in, like, יעקב, Yaakov, head over heel, like his ankle, he like
sort of tumbled down into גיהנום. Gehennom. So, why not that? אמר
רבי שמואל בר יצחק. amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Yitzchak. So רבי שמואל
בר יצחק Rabbi Shmuel bar Yitzchak said: יעקב ביקש רחמים על עצמו.
Yaakov bikkeish rachamim al atzmo. So, you know, יעקב Yaakov didn't want
to be associated with this, so it stopped a generation before him.
שנאמר בסודם אל תבוא נפשי. she'ne'emar be'sodam al tavo nafshi. And this
is
where he actually is remonstrating שמעון ולוי. Shimon ve'Levi.
So he said, בסודם אל תבוא נפשי ובקהלם אל תחד כבודי. be'sodam
al tavo nafshi uve'kehalem al techad kevodi. So I don't want to
be any part of their packs and secrets and machinations. You know,
don't let me be mentioned there. בסודם אל תבוא נפשי אלו מרגלים.
be'sodam al tavo nafshi elu meraglim. This refers to מרגלים. meraglim. ובקהלם
אל תחד כבודי זה עדת קורח, uve'kehalem al techad kevodi zeh adat
Korach, where יעקב's Yaakov name is not mentioned over there. So that's
why he's left out. So he could have been left in, we
would have darshened it the way we've been doing, but יעקב Yaakov
just got a... based on his own request, a pass. So, you
know, רש"י Rashi says, מרגלים דלא כתיב בהם פלוני בן יעקב. meraglim
dela ketiv bahem ploni ben Yaakov. You know, יעקב Yaakov is just,
you know, when they mention, you know, like the people, so-and-so ben
so-and-so, you always do that, so-and-so ben so-and-so, it doesn't go back
to יעקב. Yaakov. Okay. Now that we're darshening these names, his compatriots
over there: דתן Dathan שעבר על דת. she'avar al dat. You know,
שעבר על דת, she'avar al dat, like, you know, he... Okay, אבירם
*Aviram*, the next one שאיבר עצמו מעשות תשובה teshuvah, *she'ibber atzmo me'asot
teshuvah*. רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* doesn't really say anything. So that's—it's a strange
way of saying
this. I don't know exactly like, we sort of have like אביר
יעקב *Avir Yaakov*, right? Now, as אוויר *avir* is in air, but
like אביר יעקב *Avir Yaakov*, we have this in הפטרות *haftarot*
that the strength of יעקב *Yaakov*, אבירים *avirim* are viewed as a
strong one. So איבר עצמו *iver atzmo*,
so he sort of strengthened himself מעשות תשובה teshuvah *me'asot teshuvah* from
doing תשובה *teshuvah*. So he steeled himself to continue along this path.
Okay, so that's
דתן *Datan* and that's אבירם *Aviram*, and then the third one is
און *On* שישב באנינות *sheyashav ba'aninut*. So he sort of sat in
mourning. So
what is that?
We'll see that if someone is an אונן *onen*, that means they're
still alive, right? אונן *onen* is mourning someone else who's lost.
So we're going to see in a moment, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
actually says
it: שישב באנינות
שעשה תשובה *sheyashav ba'aninut she'asa teshuvah*. Just look at the רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*: שעשה תשובה על שהיה עמהם תחילה בעצה
*she'asa teshuvah al shehayah imahem techilah be'eitzah*. So why was it שישב
באנינות *sheyashav
ba'aninut*? Because he
was with all these people but he did תשובה *teshuvah*, so he
didn't die. So he's in mourning, I guess, for the rest of
them, or he's mourning himself, how close he got. Anyway, so he's
in a position to do that as opposed to having been killed.
And then ואון *Ve-On*, so that's און *On* בן פלת *ben Pelet*,
שנעשו לו פלאות
*shenasu lo pla'ot*.
So he
had miracles, if you will, נסים ונפלאות *nissim venifla'ot*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
again: שפירש שניצל מהם *shepeirash shenitzal mehem*.
So it was a miracle that he managed to get out. Meaning
like,
I think what they're trying to say is not there was any
particular miracle, it's not like fire came down from heaven or something
like that, but in some sense when you're so committed to a
certain path, it's very difficult to separate yourself from it. So I
think it was sort of like a miracle he managed to get
out of it, that's what I think they're saying.
So we're not—so it's not דרשנינג *darshening* him negatively because he managed
to get out. He didn't actually follow through with this. Okay, so
that's און *On*, שישב באנינות *yashav ba'aninut*, פלת שנעשו לו פלאות *Pelet
shenasu lo pla'ot*, and then the last part is בן ראובן Reuven.
*ben Reuven*, בן שראה והבין *ben shera'ah vehevin*. He saw what was
going on and he understood and he made the right decision to
not continue. אמר רב rav *Amar Rav*, so now we're going to
explain how that managed to happen, that he didn't continue along this
path. און בן פלת On ben Pelet אשתו הצילתו *On ben Pelet
ishto hitzilato*. So his wife—we're going to go up—we're going to mention,
compare and contrast to women: און בן פלת *On ben Pelet*'s wife
as opposed to that of קרח Korach *Korach*. So און בן פלת
*On ben Pelet*'s wife dissuaded him, and קרח Korach *Korach*'s wife encouraged
him. So here's the story. אמרה ליה amra lei, מאי נפקא לך
מינך *Amra lei mai nafka lach minach?* אי מר רבה אנת תלמידא
ואי מר רבה אנת תלמידא *im Mar Rabba at talmida ve-im Mar
Rabba at talmida*. No matter what, you're still going to be second
fiddle, right? משה Moshe *Moshe* wins, who are you going to be?
קרח Korach *Korach* wins, who are you going to be? So why
bother? אמר לה ומאי אעביד *Amar lah u-mai avid?* So alright, what
can I do? I'm already in this. הא אישתבעי לי בהדייהו *Ha
ishtavei li bahadeihu*. I'm part of this, I already swore that I'd
continue, what am I going to do? So אמרה ליה *amra lei*,
I'll take care of it. ידענא דכולה כנישתא קדישתא נינהו *Yad'ana dekhulah
kenishta qadisha ninhu*. I know that everyone is so holy, or at
least I think they're so holy, says כי כל העדה כולם קדושים
*ki khol ha'edah kulam kedoshim*. Everyone is holy. אמרה ליה תוב דאנא
מצילנא לך *Amra lei tuv de-ana matzilna lach*. Alright, so תוב *tuv*,
stay here, I'm going to save you. תוב *tuv* is in sit
or return. So stop, don't continue, I'll take care of it. So
what did she do? אשקיתיה חמרא *Ashkitei chamra*, so she gave him
something to drink. וארויתיה *ve'arveitei*, so he—he became a little שיכור *shikker*.
ואגניתיה גואי
*ve'agnitei gavai*, then she had to put him in inside in some
recesses of the tent. אותיבה על בבא *Oteva al bava*, and then
she sat on the פתח *petach*, בבא *bava* as in בבא מציעא
*Bava Metzia*, she sat on the door of the tent, the opening.
וסתרתיה למזיה *vesatratrei
lemazyei*, and then she let down her hair. So being in a
state of near-nakedness, right, so כל דאתא חזא הדר *kol de-ata chaza
hadar*.
So whoever saw her like this, I can't go anywhere near her,
but כי כל העדה כולם קדושים *ki khol ha'edah kulam kedoshim*, right?
Even if they weren't, they had to turn to come and to
play.
So
they turned away. So no one else, so no one could get
him, right? To continue, because he was
drunk and they weren't going to go in and wake him up,
because she's sitting there with her hair uncovered. אדהכי והכי, so you
know, meanwhile everything happened and you know, he was like sleeping it
off. So that's... so you know, which is interesting. So it's not
like he did תשובה, right?
She just saved his hide. And nevertheless, you know, he
was willing to get out.
Yeah, exactly, I was going to say that. Yeah, exactly. He, you
know, he... that was my next point. Like you know, he didn't
exactly do תשובה but you know, he sort of started along the
way. At least, you know, that I won't continue. So he gets
at least credit for that and and again, not like making things
any worse
for
himself or anyone else.
Isn't it written in רש"י, Rashi they state earlier that he did
eventually
repent? Maybe. On 38, still on the previous page.
Okay, but anyway. All right, that's און בן פלת's wife. So here's
the other one. It is קרח Korach... on the other hand, his
wife. אמרה ליה, חזי מאי קא
עביד משה. chazi mai ka-aveid Moshe. Look what משה's Moshe doing, you
know, he's consolidating his power and there'll be nothing left for you.
איהו הוי מלכא. ihu avei malka. Look what משה's Moshe doing, you
know, he's the king basically, right? You know, he's the leader, no
gainsaying him. לאחוה שוייה כהנא רבא. le-achvei shaveiyei kahana raba.
And conveniently he made his brother the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. לבני
אחוהי livnei achei and all the rest of לויים, Levi'im, of which
קרח Korach, was one. שוינו סגני דכהנא. shavinu seganei de-khana.
Yeah, but what's the purpose of the לויים, Levi'im, right? They're meant
to serve the כהנים. Kohanim. So you know, it's all about him
and his brother.
And even אי עשית תרומה, i asit terumah, אמריתו לכהן. amretu le-kohen.
If there's any תרומה, terumah, who does that go to? The כהן.
Kohen. יהבו מעשר, yahavu maaser,
the לויים Levi'im do get מעשר, maaser, but דאשכנו עשית עמא הוא
חי מיוד דכהן. dashkenu asit am hahu chai me-yud de-kohen. Right, but
even לויים Levi'im have to give a part of their מעשר maaser
to the כהן. Kohen. So no matter what, the כהן Kohen his
hands in everything. ועוד דגזייה למזייכו. ve-od de-gaza lei le-mazyeichu.
We just had that a second before, למזיי, le-mazyei, right? So as
part of the purification process for לויים, Levi'im, they had to shave
all their hair. So you know, look how stupid you're all looking.
He's saying, ותוב לכו כקופתא, vatu le-chu ke-kufta, right? So... and עינא
יהב במזייכו. eina yaha be-mazyeichu. What, you know, he's looking after all
your hair? He must... you know, he's jealous, you know, that...
and he's going to make you look all so silly.
I still can't get how he shaved those tens of thousands of
Levites all in one day. Yeah, and he was 83 years old.
That's right, at least, right? אמרה ליה הא איהו נמי
קא עביד.
amra lei ha ihu
nami ke-aveid. So קרח Korach, responded, yeah, משה's Moshe a לוי, Levi,
so if we have to do it, he's doing it too. אמרה
ליה כיון דכולא דידיה. amra lei keivan de-kula dedei. אמר איהו נמי
תמות נפשי עם פלשתים. amar ihu nami tamut nafshi im pelishtim. Yeah,
I mean, it's really like he's doing it, but he's doing it
really more to denigrate you. He has to go along with it,
right? Sort of like שמשון Shimshon said, תמות נפשי עם פלשתים, tamut
nafshi im pelishtim, you know,
if I can't beat them, we all die together. So משה Moshe
saw, like, you know, something he has to do, but it's really
all about, you know, at the end of the day, he's doing
it as a power grab. ועוד
דאמר לכו עבידו תכלת. ve-od de-amar le-chu veidu techeilet.
So you know, and משה Moshe, said, you know, this whole... because
right after קרח... Korach. around קרח, Korach. right? You have מרגלים, Meraglim,
you have right שלח, Shelach, קרח, Korach and in שלח Shelach is
פרשת ציצית. parshat tzitzit. And then there's the פרשה parshah of קרח.
Korach. So that's what she's talking about with this תכלת. techeilet. So
you just got told about having to make these תכלת, techeilet, this,
you know, on
your
fringes of whatever it is you need to be wearing. איהו דעבד
לה לתכלת חשיבא. ihu de-avad le-techeilet chashiva.
It's so important, דאי מייתי תכלת דחסינו כולם מיפטר. de-i meiti techeilet
de-chasinu kulu metiftach.
So here he didn't actually, you know, you know there's another מדרש
midrash about like how I'm sure some of you are familiar with
it, how they got up and they made themselves all dressed in
תכלת, techeilet, like a full טלית tallit of תכלת, techeilet, not just
the, you know, the ends, not just like the one חוט, chut,
right? And said, oh, well, you know, if it's so important, do
we have to put תכלת techeilet in a טלית tallit of all
תכלת? techeilet? And they started mocking. So this is, I think, an
allusion. It doesn't get into the rest of it. So anyway, make
everybody have תכלת techeilet and then, you know,
doesn't say what happens, but anyway this might be as I said
the allusion. Anyway, חכמות נשים בנתה ביתה. hachmon nashim banta beita. So
חכמות
נשים, hachmon nashim, the wise
ones build their homes. That would be אשתו של און בן פלת
ishto shel On ben Pelet who managed to get him out of
this so she, you know, she was smart about it. But the
rest of the פסוק pasuk is ואולת בידיה
תהרסנו ve-ivelet be-yadeha tehersenu
or בידה be-yada
תהרסה tehersa or תהרסנו, tehersennu, but the foolish one, you know, as
opposed to the smart wife that's helping build the house, a foolish
one is taking an active role in destroying it. That would be
the wife of קרח. Korach
אשתו של קרח. ishto shel Korach. So continuing with the story, ויקומו
לפני משה ואנשים מבני ישראל חמשים ומאתים. vayakumu lifnei Moshe ve-anashim mi-bnei
Yisrael chamishim u-matayim. So who are these people that rise up to
משה, Moshe these 250 people? The גמרא Gemara says, I mean the
תורה Torah says, נשיאי עדה קריאי מועד אנשי שם. nesi'ei eidah keriei
mo'ed anshei shem. מיוחדים שבעדה. meyuchadim she-be-eidah. Okay,
so they're the, you know, the chosen ones, the special ones of
the of the people, not just anybodies. קריאי מועד. keriei mo'ed.
So what does it say, קריאי מועד? keriei mo'ed? What does that
mean? שהיו יודעים לעבר שנים ולקבוע חודשים, Shehayu yodeim le-aber shanim ve-likboa
chodashim, right? This is a harkening back to the very beginning of
the מסכת. masechet. Yeah, they were, they were really, they really knew
their stuff, they were the special ones, you know, not everyone can
be מעבר שנים, me-aber shanim, you know, make an עיבור שנה ibbur
shanah or לקבוע חודשים, likboa chodashim,
set the months. אנשי שם שהיה עליהם שם בכל העולם, Anshei shem
she-alehem shem be-chol ha-olam, you know, not just amongst the Jewish people.
They were well known, you know,
because of their wisdom.
This is a repeating theme, people who are great תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim can still be wrong.
Yeah.
You know, I guess that's, I mean in some ways it's the
גמרא's Gemara way to like nuance them, that like you know, not
to be evil or only evil, right, you know? But then again,
not to necessarily because you know and do מצוות mitzvot it doesn't
make you a good person, but you know, but we just want
to add a layer of complexity here.
You know, this is, this is a theological problem that people doing
מצוות, mitzvot, learning a lot, and they still do evil.
Yeah.
You know, their learning was just so, you know, in some ways
superficial. וישמע משה ויפל על פניו, Vayishma Moshe vayipol al panav,
that משה Moshe. heard this and you know, fell on his face.
So מה שמועה שמע, mah shmuah shama, what did he hear? I
mean, you know, well the פשט pshat is he heard what exactly
was happening, you know, that they're challenging משה. Moshe, So ויפל פניו,
vayipol panav, that's a way of him like saying, you know, you
bow down, you balance submission, okay, you know, I abdicate my leadership
in some way, right? So anyway, so we're,
we're going to דרשן darshen it.
אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן שחשדוהו מאשת איש. Amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan she-chashduhu me-eshet ish. So they
suspected him of adultery. שנאמר ויקנאו למשה במחנה. Shenemar vayikanu le-Moshe ba-machaneh.
So as it says, ויקנאו למשה מחנה. vayikanu le-Moshe machaneh. So,
you know, literally that means like, you know, we have פנחס Pinchas
and השם Hashem בקנאו את קנאתי, be-kano et kinati, you know, he's
zealous, he stood up for my honor, so that's what it means.
But
we also know from סוטה, Sotah, וקנא את אשתו, ve-kina et ishto,
right? If
someone is
asserting his his rights, so to speak, over his wife, and you
know, he does this process called קינוי וסתירה. kinui ve-stira. So it's
that's the play on that, that, you know, he says, you know,
you can't be with so-and-so. So that's what they all did. אמר
רבי שמואל בר יצחק מלמד שכל אחד ואחד קינא את אשתו ממשה.
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Yitzchak: Melamed she-kol echad ve-echad kina et ishto
mi-Moshe. So
they all, you know, said that. שנאמר משה יקח את האהל ונטה
לו מחוץ למחנה. Shenemar Moshe yikach et ha-ohel u-nata lo mi-chutz la-machaneh.
So
משה, Moshe this was at the time
where you had this back in שמות, Shemot, but you know, back
when בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, you know, the whole חטא העגל Chet
ha-Egel thing, right, before the משכן, Mishkan, משה Moshe took his אהל
מועד, Ohel Moed, right? So he you know, sort of retreated from
everybody. And then God's presence returned after the building of the משכן.
Mishkan. But you know, they're saying, oh, you know, there's the way
I interpret it, and also other interpretations. But yeah, now they're saying,
oh, why did he put his tent so far away? You know,
he's doing something that you know, no one should be seen. So
all right, it must be that he's like you know with all
our wives. Same, the point is
less than you know, that
that's really what they're suspecting him of, but you know, how do
you start a rumor? Right, you have everyone like sort of saying
something, right? It doesn't have to be true, it doesn't have to
have any remote
you know, tie-in to fact, but you have enough people saying something,
and you get people talking. So you know, and and
no one wants to be, no one's going to say, oh well
he's a, he's a like you know,
he's an adulterer, you know, you can't be safe around him, he's
going to you know, sleep with your wives, but no one's going
to want to follow. That's the idea, you know, just sort of
eroding his power base with vicious rumors. What the rumor was makes
no difference. You have enough people saying it, you know, then it
gets legs. So
anyway, ויקם משה וילך אל דתן ואבירם.
vayakom Moshe vayelech el
Datan ve-Aviram. So he gets up and goes to דתן ואבירם, Datan
ve-Aviram, you know, despite everything that they're trying to do. מכאן שאין
מחזיקים במחלוקת. Mikan she-ein machzikim be-machloket. Don't continue the
מחלוקת. machloket. Like משה Moshe is trying to make peace. דאמר רב
כל המחזיק במחלוקת עובר בלאו. Damar Rav: Kol ha-machzik be-machloket over be-lav.
So not just good advice, but it's actually a לאו. lav. שנאמר
ולא יהיה כקרח וכעדתו. Shenemar lo yihyeh ke-Korach ve-che-adato. You know, not
to be like קרח Korach and his עדה. edah. So
the way most of us would take that, and the way one
would think to take it is that, you know, in other words
don't like rebel, you know, against השם. Hashem. But you know, here
he's saying like you know, not just that, but just in general,
if there's a dispute, don't you know, don't entrench yourself in your
position. I mean as far as I know, you know, this is
more of a like moral point and it's not like the רמב"ם
Rambam counts this you know, as one of the תרי"ג מצוות. taryag
mitzvot. You know what I mean? Like you know, if you go
through the תרי"ג מצוות, taryag mitzvot, this isn't one of them. But
nevertheless, it's still a good point.
Okay. So that's
that's on that. ורב אשי Ve-Rav Ashi continuing that, אמר רב אשי
כל המחזיק במחלוקת ראוי להצטרע. Amar Rav Ashi: Kol ha-machzik be-machloket ra-uy
le-hitstara'e. That you're deserving of צרעת. tzara'at. כתיב הכא ביד משה לו.
Ketiv hacha be-yad Moshe lo.
That's in the end, ולא יהיה כקרח וכעדתו כאשר דבר השם ביד
משה לו.
ve-lo yihyeh ke-Korach ve-che-adato ka-asher diber Hashem
be-yad Moshe lo. That's that same פסוק. pasuk. And the hand, what
does it say, ביד משה? be-yad Moshe? וכתיב התם ויאמר השם לו
עוד הבא נא ידך בחיקך. U-chetiv hatam: Vayomer Hashem lo od ha-ve
na yadecha be-cheikecha.
And you know, when השם Hashem is telling משה Moshe all these
signs to perform to the Jewish people and then you know in
front of פרעה, Paroh,
משה Moshe, says how will they believe me and then you know...
one of the signs was putting his hand in his garment, his
pocket, and then taking it out and then at that time what's
צרעת? tzaraat? So יד היד, yad hayad, so whoever is מחזיק מחלוקת
machzik machloket deserves to get צרעת. tzaraat. Although, you know, again, it's
if the other גמרות Gemaras talk about the reasons for צרעת, tzaraat,
מחלוקת machloket isn't one of them, you know what I mean? But,
you know, again, this is more the moral point than anything. אמר
רב יוסי, Amar Rav Yosei, כל החולק על המלכות, kol hacholek al
hamalchut, על מלכות בית דוד, al malchut Beit David, and now we're
talking about that, insurrections. So whoever just, you know, חולק על המלכות,
cholek al hamalchut, you know, just rebels, disagrees, whatever, you know, is
causing trouble, ראוי להכישו נחש, raui lehachisho nachash, you know, deserves to
be bitten
by a נחש, nachash, a deadly
snake. דכתיב D'chtiv ויזבח אדניהו צאן ובקר ומריא
עם
אבן הזוחלת.
va-yizbach Adoniyahu tzon u-vakar
u-meri
im even hazochelet. So
אדניהו Adoniyahu who was one of the children of דוד David who
rebelled against him, so he’s making all these sacrifices by this place
אבן הזוחלת, even hazochelet, which is a very strange term, like לזחול
lizchol is to crawl, right? And rocks don’t move, but anyway, I
mean that’s what it was called. But anyway, but another פסוק pasuk
דכתיב, d'chtiv, so, so זוחלת zochelet דהתם de-hatam חמת זוחלי עפר chamat
zochalei afar with, you know, with the קללה, klalah, חמת זוחלי עפר,
chamat zochalei afar, the anger of those that crawl on the ground,
like, you know, what slithers on the ground, better
slither. So נחש, nachash, so, yeah, whoever is rebelling against מלכות בית
דוד malchut Beit David deserves to be bitten by a snake. אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, כל החולק על רבו, kol hacholek al
rabo, now that we’re into that, whoever disagrees... and again, I don’t
think it means just like disagree like, oh, you know, I think
a פשט pshat this way, you know, if again you’re like, you
know, really
going
against his halachic rulings I think is what it, what it is,
right? You’re really questioning but not in a like a question like
as in, you know, I think oh,
you know, maybe your basis for this ruling is wrong in a
respectful way, but like, you know, like, oh, you know, I don’t
care what you say, you know, I’m going to disagree with you
and I don’t want to listen to you, that kind of thing,
I think that’s what it means. כל החולק על רבו כחולק על
השכינה.
kol hacholek al rabo
kicholek al haShechinah. So doing against your רב rav is... and I
think there's a רש"י Rashi over here. Is there?
I
don’t know. Oh, yeah, חולק על רבו cholek al rabo is חולק
על ישיבתו, cholek al yishivato, רש"י Rashi. says ישיבתו. yishivato. What does,
you know, I think it means like, you know, challenging his legitimacy,
right? חולק על ישיבתו. cholek al yishivato.
So
and again, not just like, you know, they're having a halachic dispute
kind of thing. I mean the גמרא Gemara does that all the
time, right? People disagree with their רבנים rabbanim but are challenging, you
know, said oh, how can you say that then we learned something
else somewhere
else? That’s not a... so here it means like, you know, in
a real, it’s a challenge, like the other challenges we’ve had. Okay,
anyway, so like doing that is חולק על השכינה, cholek al haShechinah,
is like doing is going against God, שנאמר, shenemar, בהצותם על השם.
bahatzotam al Hashem.
Like again, עדת קרח, adat Korach, they disagreed with God. So that’s
really what it was about. אמר רב חמא ברבי חנינא, Amar Rav
Chama b'rebi Chanina, כל העושה מריבה עם רבו כעושה עם שכינה. kol
ha'oseh merivah im rabo k'oseh im Shechinah. So same idea,
doing
that, you know, having this these fightings, you know,
fighting with the רב rav is like fighting with God, שנאמר, shenemar,
המה מי מריבה אשר רבו בני ישראל על השם. heimah Mei Merivah
asher ravu Bnei Yisrael al Hashem. So מי מריבה, Mei Merivah, you
know, they're complaining against משה, Moshe, but
you know, they were like we want to drink something, right? They
were they were getting all upset. So
but the גמרא, Gemara, yeah, but the תורה Torah says it's, you
know, that it was against God. So going against a רב rav,
is like going against God. אמר חנינא בר פפא, Amar Chanina bar
Papa, כל המתראם, kol hamitra'em, you know, it's hard to understand exactly
what the differences are between all this:
the החולק hacholek versus the מריבה merivah versus the מתראם. mitra'em. But
I think it's basically saying the same thing just to get to
the
פסוקים. psukim. מתראם, mitra'em, so
here he... so רש"י Rashi starts to explain, מריבה, merivah, he said
תגר והסתבב וקטטנים נגד
רבו, tagar v'histatev v'katfanim neged rabo, just like, you know, being intentionally
not just like difficult, like I think sort of like obstructionist, right?
That's מריבה. merivah. You like getting into all these
fights. מתראם mitra'em is
אומר על רבו שנוהג לו מידה כבושה ומידת אכזרית.
omer al rabo shenoheg
lo midah kevushah u'midat achzarit. So מתראם mitra'em is either that's more
about personally, you know,
you're being cruel, you're being
whatever.
That's what that is. So if you do that, again, just the
same idea, if you do it against your רב, rav it's like
you're doing it against God. מתראם על השכינה, mitra'em al haShechinah, שנאמר,
shenemar, לא עלינו תלונותיכם. lo aleinu telunoteichem. This is with the מן.
man. So
it’s
not you when they when they complain to משה, Moshe. he’s saying
it’s not your complaint is really directed against me, it’s against God.
אמר רב אבהו, Amar Rav Abbahu, כל המהרהר אחר רבו כמהרהר אחר
שכינה. kol hamharher achar rabo k'meharher achar Shechinah.
המהרהר Hamharher is, רש"י explains, מחפה עליו דברים. mechapeh alav devarim. which
is again it’s just a little bit
difficult to translate, so
but it’s the same idea, you know. It’s like you think bad
things about him.
So that’s if you do that, that’s like doing it against Hashem.
שנאמר shene'emar וידבר העם באלוהים ובמשה. Vayidaber ha'am be'Elokim ube'Moshe. And this
is again a פסוק pasuk again when the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
were complaining they spoke out against and here it mentions like, you
know, even God first, God and משה. Moshe, So speaking again, this
is again like another thing. Again, when they had no food, they’re
like, you know, they’re like why did you have to take us
out from here from Egypt? We’d rather stay there. There’s no food,
there’s no water, and you know, we’re all going to die. So
but they’re talking to משה, Moshe but you know,
it’s באלוהים ובמשה. be'Elokim ube'Moshe.
All right, עושר שמור לבעליו לרעתו, osher shamur liva'alav lera'ato, which is
it will cause, you know, the downfall of somebody. אמר ריש לקיש
זה עושרו של קרח. Amar Reish Lakish, zeh oshro shel Korach. This
is referring to the riches of קרח. Korach
And he explains ואת כל היקום אשר ברגליהם. ve'et kol hayikum asher
beragleihem.
So when the land opens up and swallows them all, ותבלע אותם
ואת בתיהם, vativla osam ve'et bateihem, something like that, ואת כל היקום
אשר ברגליהם. ve'et kol hayikum asher beragleihem. So it swallows them, you
know, their houses. And what’s ואת כל היקום אשר ברגליהם? ve'et kol
hayikum asher beragleihem? What does that mean?
So יקום yikum is in
לקום. lakum. So it’s, you know, it’s all their possessions really, not
just their but not just their but everything else they had, right?
Their cattle or whatever, right? אמר רבי אלעזר זה ממונו של אדם
שמעמידו על רגליו. Amar Rabbi Elazar, zeh mamono shel adam shema'amido al
raglav. So this is their money because that literally gives you standing.
אמר רבי לוי, Amar Rabbi Levi, now introduced the fact that קרח
Korach? was so rich, well you want rich, I'll tell you how
rich. משוי ג' מאות פרדות לבנות היו מפתחות של בית גנזיו של
קרח. Masoy gimmel me'os perados livanos hayu maftechos shel beis genazav shel
Korach. So
he had three hundred, you know, white mules
carrying worth of stuff. And that stuff isn't just his riches, three
hundred mules is quite a lot, that was an exaggeration but this,
you know, obviously three hundred mules is a total lot but that's
not just his stuff, that's just like the keys to his treasure
houses. So imagine how rich he was. And these keys, and don't
think they were really big heavy keys, כולא קלידי וקלידי דגלדא, kula
klidei veklidei degilda, it's like these light leather keys, right, so you
know, it's not like these so that's how rich he was. He
had all that.
Steinsaltz has a picture with an ancient key.
Is it leather? No, looks like it's stone.
Yeah, looks like never heard of a leather key.
Yeah, okay. And so how did he get so rich? אמר רב
חמא
ברבי חנינא ג' מטמוניות הטמין יוסף.
Amar Rav Chama be'Rabbi Chanina, gimmel matmoniyos hitmin
Yosef. So remember, you know, in the גמרא's Gemara's view, so יוסף
Yosef gathered the wealth. He gathered the wealth of all the surrounding
land. So you know, so he yeah, it's not like but the
fact is the whole world but the region but you know יוסף
Yosef got really rich from all this, the king, the government, yeah.
So anyway, so what'd he do with all the money? So three
they were hidden. אחת נתגלתה לקרח, Achas
nisgalta le'Korach, so קרח Korach. found one of
them. ואחת נתגלתה לאנטונינוס בן אסוירוס. ve'achas nisgalta le'Antoninus ben Asveirus. That
is the that is the אנטונינוס Antoninus that the גמרא Gemara refers
to as being רבי's, Rebbi's, you know, friend.
So קרח Korach,
found one, אנטונינוס Antoninus found one, ואחת גנוזה לצדיקים לעתיד לבוא, ve'achas
genuzah le'tzadikim le'asid lavo, or no one found it and you know
we'll find it at some future point. So that's how he was
so rich. That's, you know, so much so that even have like
300 white
mules carrying the stuff. What's with the white mules?
Probably like, you know, they were like ancient watchdogs in the גמרא's
Gemara's eyes because you know all these white things like, you know,
were supposed to be like really dangerous. So if they, you know,
like the גמרא Gemara elsewhere talks about a white mule if it
bites you then, you know, you don't you don't recover. So they
were probably like, you know, guard mules so to speak, so you
know no one comes it'll bite them and you know they'll die.
So you know that was a safe way to keep them. He
couldn't bury them, right, because he kept on traveling from place to
place. Yeah, what?
Steinsaltz thinks that's a different emperor, that it's אנטונינוס Antoninus son of
ספטימוס סוורוס Septimus Severus who is better known by the name of
Caracalla who
ruled 212 to 217.
So not the רבי? Rebbi?
Because רבי Rebbi was probably still alive but not the not the
one with whom רבי Rebbi had philosophical
discussions.
He was known as a
spendthrift, so this might be where he got his wealth, but he
also gave citizenship to anyone who lived in the empire, which was
a really big deal.
Yeah, okay.
Artscroll does
think it's the one who was a friend with רבי. Rebbi.
Yeah, I know, but every time you have an אנטונינוס Antoninus it's
the one that’s a friend of
רבי Rebbi in the גמרא, Gemara, I mean you know. Most people
do.
Yes, Steinsaltz, yeah, but because of the בן אסוירוס ben Asveirus is
apparently the reason. But that particular emperor was the son of ספטימוס
סוורוס, Septimus Severus, let me see if he has another name, every
emperor seemed to have lots of names.
Yeah, okay, continuing here. We'll start ואמר רבי יוחנן קרח לא מן
הבלועים ולא מן השרופים. ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan Korach lo min ha-belu'im ve-lo
min ha-serufim. So remember, like, you know, there're two things that go
on. There're with דתן ואבירם, Datan ve-Aviram, that whole part, that משה
Moshe says, alright, let the earth open up and swallow them. But
then there were still the 250 people doing the קטורת Ketoret and
those people got burnt, right? So what happened to
קרח? Korach Because we'll see, we'll look at the פסוקים Pesukim why
it might be some ambiguity or not.
So this first opinion is he didn't get either of those punishments.
כתיב ואת כל האדם אשר לקרח ותפתח הארץ את פיה ותבלע אותם,
kethiv ve-et kol ha-adam asher le-Korach va-tiftach ha-aretz et piha va-tivla otam,
that whole thing we were just quoting a minute ago. It says
את כל האדם אשר לקרח, et kol ha-adam asher le-Korach, all the
people with קרח. Korach But all the people with
קרח, Korach. not קרח Korach himself. So you think okay, you know,
he was elsewhere because he was supposed to be part of this
whole test with the קטורת. Ketoret. Wait, let me just finish this
one. So he's supposed to be part of the test with the
קטורת. Ketoret. So, you know, it was him and the 250 people.
ולא מן השרופים, ve-lo min ha-serufim, not there either. דכתיב ואש אכלה
את חמשים ומאתים איש. de-kethiv ve-esh achlah et chamishim u-matayim ish. It
consumed the 250 people. If קרח Korach. was there, it would be
251. Obviously, you know, they're rounding. But you know, if you want
to say that he was from the שרופים, serufim, so he wasn't
from the בלועים belu'im and not from the שרופים, serufim, so what
happened to him?
You could say that, and רש"י I think
says...
I saw it somewhere. Let me look it up to it in
a minute. All right, wait a minute, if not I'll tell you.
What were you going to say, Charlie?
Yeah, so שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz is probably right because that emperor's original did
have the name
Antoninus, and Severus was his father's name. So it's interesting, it's a
different Antoninus.
לא מן הבלועים ולא מן השרופים. lo min ha-belu'im ve-lo min ha-serufim.
I found the רש"י. It's the last רש"י on the right-hand column.
אלא במגפה מת. ela be-magefah met. He died from a מגפה magefah
like the מרגלים meraglim did. וימותו במגפה. va-yamutu ba-magefah. So he died
from that. Whatever the מגפה magefah was. Anyway, so he wasn't one
of those. But he died, but not the way his followers died.
That's the first opinion.
ומתניתא תנא קרח מן השרופים ומן הבלועים. u-matnita tana Korach min ha-serufim
u-min ha-belu'im. So the first opinion said he got neither of them,
second opinion says he got both. מן הבלועים, min ha-belu'im, דכתיב
ותבלע אותם ואת קרח. de-kethiv va-tivla otam ve-et Korach.
Yeah, what do you do about that, right?
It
swallowed them and
קרח. Korach מן השרופים, min ha-serufim, דכתיב ותצא אש מלפני ה' ותאכל
את החמשים ומאתים איש. de-kethiv va-tetze esh mi-lifnei Hashem va-tochal et ha-chamishim
u-matayim ish. And it consumed them and קרח Korach was there.
So again, how did that happen? How do you get both? So
you could say like he got burnt and then his body rolled
down and got swallowed, some form of that. But so what does
the other opinion say, right? You can get out of
the שרופים serufim part, right?
Because all right, so maybe it burned them and not him. But
what do you... how can you possibly argue that other פסוק? pasuk?
So let me
get the פסוק pasuk for you
over
there. It actually isn't exactly
where you would expect it to be. One second. Numbers 26:10. Yeah,
no, it's easier in the חומש. Chumash. במדבר Bamidbar 26:10.
So any of you, as I was telling you, isn't exactly where
you'd expect it to be. Do you know where it is? If
anyone... so this is a little challenge. Do they have it written?
No, no, no, but what context it is, do you know?
It's not in קרח. Korach This is in פנחס. Pinchas.
No, yeah, that's what they say they explain it in.
No, no, I'll read it to you. But it talks about
the מגפה magefah that happened
with... we were talking about this before. פעור, Peor, right? When בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael were doing זנות zenut with בנות מואב. Benot Moav.
So then there's a מגפה magefah that killed, you know, killed at
least 24,000 people. After the מגפה, magefah, השם Hashem says, all right,
you've got to start counting everybody. Then they go through the genealogy.
So it talks about ראובן. ובני אליאב נמואל ודתן ואבירם הוא דתן
ואבירם קריאי
העדה אשר הצו על משה ועל
אהרן בעדת קרח בהצתם על ה'.
u-vnei Eliav Nemuel ve-Datan ve-Aviram hu Datan ve-Aviram keri'ei ha-edah asher hitzu
al Moshe
ve-al
Aharon be-adat Korach be-hatzotam al Hashem. So it's referring to the קרח
Korach rebellion. Yeah, I know, but I'm saying it's not mentioned in
פרשת קרח. Parshat Korach. So that's why I say it's not the
context you'd expect it to be.
So let me lean this to you, and here's where I think,
and I think I'll start my plug because I do a lot
of leaning, but this is where I think leaning actually helps. Sometimes
like leaning actually gives you a פשט pshat on the פסוק pasuk
or creates. creates an ambiguity where you think everything is so simple.
I'll lean it the אשכנזי Ashkenazi so most of you can understand
it: ותפתח הארץ את פיה ותבלע אתם ואת קרח במות העדה. Vatiftach
ha'aretz et piha vatival otam ve'et Korach bemot ha'edah.
Now what did I do? I didn't say ותבלע אתם, vatival otam,
right?
Then if it was מהפך פשטא זקף גדול, mapach pashta zakef gadol,
ותבלע אתם ואת קרח, vatival otam ve'et Korach,
then it means then that's all connected, right? But listen to the
words: ותבלע אתם... vatival otam... ואת קרח במות העדה, ve'et Korach bemot
ha'edah, right?
So it could be you either read it with the אתם, otam,
אתם ואת קרח, otam ve'et Korach,
or you can do ואת קרח במות העדה, ve'et Korach bemot ha'edah,
right? So קרח died במות העדה. bemot ha'edah. And what you know
what עדה edah can also mean like עדת מרגלים, adat meraglim, like
מגפה magefah which is you know or we can say you know
anyway that's how you can get out of that that you know
the other פשט pshat this the other the other opinion right the
that's why that's that's do you get it?
Yeah so there's no punctuation in the
תורה Torah yeah so that's why the leaning is sometimes to give
that that certain ambiguity that's how the other one can maybe get
out of it they'd say that he died with a מגפה magefah
במות העדה bemot ha'edah like that's talking about a different עדה. edah.
So so like you just put a semicolon in the English text.
Ah yeah English but I mean you
know not safe to make a separation which is what you're doing
making a separation yeah.
But I'm saying the טראפ trop can you know lead to that
different understanding.
Right right right right right.
So okay
that's that other opinion so either he died totally in a different
way or he got both. אמר מר Amar
Mar מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv שמש ירח עמד
זבלה לאור חציך יהלכו,
shemesh yareiach amad zevulah
le'or chitzecha yehalechu, פסוק pasuk
saying basically the שמש shemesh the sun the moon עמד זבלה amad
zevulah so they stood in the זבול zevul
is one of the words for like you know whatever however
this actually works like different like spheres of heaven so like you
know that's where they were up in that sphere of heaven. So
לאור חציך יהלכו le'or chitzecha yehalechu they לאור חציך le'or chitzecha
חצים chitzim is arrows so so
like you know so there's some sort of connection between light and
arrows so what's that about? מלמד שעלו שמש וירח לזבול Melamed she'alu
shemesh veyareiach lizevul so they so basically so
at this they're trying to make this referred to the rebellion of
קרח that at the time all that was happening מלמד שעלו שמש
וירח לזבול melamed she'alu shemesh veyareiach lizevul
when that was happening they went all the way up to you
know the highest heavens where God is. אמרו לפניו רבונו של עולם
אם אתה עושה דין לבן עמרם נצא ואם לאו לא נצא. Amru
lefanav Ribbono Shel Olam im ata oseh din liven Amram netzei ve'im
lav lo netzei. We are on strike. If you you know if
you manage to you know help out משה Moshe over here we'll
go we'll go out and do our normal thing if not we're
not going to go out. God did not want to hear any
of this עד שזרק בהם חצים ad she'zarak bahem chitzim so then
he had to like you know send arrows to
them and yeah but they had a good point so why why
you know so what why would God do this? He says אמר
להם בכבודי לא מחיתם בכבוד בשר ודם מחיתם. amar lahem bichvodi lo
mechitem bichvod basar vadam mechitem. Oh okay you're willing to shine for
everyone else you know people worship the sun and the moon you're
not worried about that you know why don't you say all right
if you judge these idolaters we'll go out you know so meaning
you know it's you're right to be upset you know or zealous
for משה's Moshe honor but you should be zealous for mine too
God is saying so he's like all right you're going out. So
so yeah result of this is ועדיין לא נפקי עד דמחו
להו ve'adin lo nafku ad demachu lehu so you know God had
a good point so and they're still at least the time of
the גמרא Gemara they're still these idolaters are worshipping the sun and
the moon now they still don't want to go out and God
has to like you
know shoo them out every day you know I mean he has
to like you know send arrows to them and you know make
sure that they go out because they learned their lesson then and
now they don't want to go out. So anyway so they have
to be shooed out. דרש רבא Darash Rava מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv
אם בריאה יברא ה׳ im b'riah yivra Hashem back to קרח with
the
אדמה adama opening up what is אם בריאה יברא ה׳? im b'riah
yivra Hashem? אמר משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא amar Moshe lifnei HaKadosh
Baruch Hu אם בריאה im b'riah you've created this
this new thing you know the the mouth opening up and you
know you're going to create this whole ability now
but אם בריאה היא גיהנם מוטב ואם לאו יברא ה׳ im b'riah
hi Gehennom mutav ve'im lav yivra Hashem so you know גיהנם Gehennom
was already been created for them great if not do it now
so that they can you know descend there.
So למאי? le'mai? What do you mean? How's that possible? ואין כל
חדש תחת השמש Ve'ein kol chadash tachat hashemesh משה Moshe really saying
that? והא אין כל חדש תחת השמש ve'ha ein kol chadash tachat
hashemesh משה can't be saying that nothing new like that nothing new's
created.
That's really sort of like קהלת Kohelet like you know bemoaning that
nothing new I'm bored in life you know but the things to
be literally that אין חדש תחת השמש ein chadash tachat hashemesh you
can't have a new creation. אלא לקרובי פתחון Ela lekuruvei pichon so
okay fine גיהנם Gehennom was there but what he means is you
know you gotta get there somehow right there's like you know there's
like the entrance way so you know the entrance way's here if
this is one of the places where you can actually access it
then great if not you know make the entrance come a little
closer so they can go down there and descend yes.
משנה אבות Mishna Avot addresses this
problem
yeah.
So anyway, that's what the point is that this is the answer.
Okay, now remember we had Ohm Pellet, right? He kind of got
out of this, but
when
I was reading that whole פסוק pasuk *pasuk* ותפתח הארץ פיה ותבל
אותם *vatiftach ha'aretz piha vatival otam* and swallowed them, the next פסוק
pasuk. *pasuk* is over there: Who else didn't die?
בני קרח *Bnei Korach*.
Right, בני קרח לא מתו *Bnei Korach lo metu*.
They lived long enough to write תהלים *Tehillim*.
בני קרח לא מתו *Bnei Korach lo metu*, תנא *tana*, משם רבינו
אמרו *Mishom rabbeinu amru*—משם
רבינו
*Mishom rabbeinu*, I'm sorry, משם רבינו *Mishom rabbeinu*. משם רבינו אמרו *Mishom
rabbeinu amru*. Okay, so let's darshen this. משם רבינו אמרו *Mishom rabbeinu
amru*, מקום נתבצר להם בגיהנום וישבו עליו ואמרו שירה *makom nitbatzer lahem
b'Gehinnom v'yashvu alav v'amru shira*.
So they didn't die, but they end up having
a—so it's sort of hard to explain what this means. Does it
mean like, you know, they were swallowed but like didn't die? Or
does it mean, you know, at some point, I mean, didn't die
from this מחלוקת *machloket*, but at some point they died.
And what happened to them? You know, they get a high place
in גיהנום *Gehinnom* and then they—they say שירה *shira*. So what's that
about?
I'll—I'll tell you what—I'll tell you something, but you know, I'm happy
for any of you to pipe in if you want, if you
had any thoughts about it. Anyone?
So some—my grandfather, עליו השלום *alav hashalom*, said. He said that this
is sort of
going—this is one of the two teachings I really remember very clearly.
He said that this is sort of—if you think about what we
just had before, we had Moshe going to Dathan and Abiram because
you can't be מחזיק במחלוקת *mahzik b'machloket*,
right? So בני קרח לא מתו *Bnei Korach lo metu*. At the
end of the day, they did—you know, it's one thing to Ohm
Pellet who was, like, you know, earlier on in this. בני קרח
*Bnei Korach*, I mean, one way of saying it is בני קרח
*Bnei Korach* were never part of this, right? That's why they—they didn't
die. But you can say they were part of it, right? At
the end of the day, they, you know, they did תשובה *teshuva*,
fine. But, you know, until that point, they were really like
causing
a lot of מחלוקת *machloket*. So if you cause a lot of
מחלוקת *machloket*, you know, your effects are, you know, are kind of
long-lasting. It's kind of hard to undo that, right? You can do
תשובה *teshuva* for like, oh I'm sorry I've been doing this, but
what about all the people you've incited, all the lives you've potentially
ruined, you know, and the anguish you caused to the people when
you did this? So, since they're מחזיק במחלוקת *mahzik b'machloket*, you know,
they still have to go—they still go to hell, they get a
high place, but they're still in גיהנום *Gehinnom*. So that's—that's one way
of taking it.
He was always a peacemaker. Anyway, וישבו עליו ואמרו שירה *v'yashvu alav
v'amru shira*. And now we're going to be talking about this שירה
*shira*. אמר *Amar*—this is—you may remember this—this story on רבה בר בר
חנה *Rabbah bar Bar Hana*, זימנא חדא הוה קאזילנא באורחא *zimna chada
hava kazina b'orchot*. Well, the other stories about this and you know,
in that—I think it was—where was it that had that big גמרא
*Gemara* in בבא בתרא *Bava Batra* where you know about the—they passed
by the דור המדבר dor hamidbar *Dor HaMidbar* and like, their legs
and they passed under like the crook of the legs? Remember that?
All right, if not, then it's fine. Anyway, here's one of these
stories. אמר רבה בר בר חנה *Amar Rabbah bar Bar Hana*, זימנא
חדא הוה קאזילנא באורחא *zimna chada hava kazina b'orchot*, on my way.
אמר לי ההוא טייעא *Amar lei hahu taya*, טייעא *Taya*'s always one
of these like, you know, merchants. Arab merchants, he's like, you know,
one of these nomads, whatever. תא ואחוי לך בלועי דקרח *Ta v'achavei
lach beluei Korach*. Come let me show you where they are, the
people Korach swallowed. וחזא *v'chaza*—I saw—תרי ביזעי *tra bezi*, so
he saw like, you know, some cracks in the ground. הוה קא
נפק קוטרא מנייהו *havah ka nafak kitra mineihu*, like smoke was coming
up from them. שקל גבבא דעמרא *shakal gabba d'amra*, so he took
like a ball of wool, עמרא *amra* is צמרא *samra* is צמר
*tzemer*. אמשי מיא *amshi maya*, soaked it in water, ואוזי בראש רומחא
*v'otzi b'reish rumcha*, you know, you don't want to get too close
so he put it at the end of like, you know, like
a stick, right? So ואחוי התם *v'achvei hatam* and איחרך *ichrach*, you
know, in spite of the fact that this was like dripping wet,
it still got like singed. *Shreiyo hatav*—that smoke. *Aiyei*, these thermals, right?
אמר לי *Amar lei*, צית מאי שמעת *tzeit mai shamat*.
So then and this guy said, all right, go—צית *tzeit*, like, you
know, listen to what you're going to hear. ושמעית דהוו קא אמרי
הכי *v'shama'it d'havu ka amri hachi*: משה ותורתו אמת *Moshe v'torato emet*.
Yeah, משה אמת ותורתו אמת *Moshe emet v'torato emet*, that—yeah, that song.
והן בדאין *v'hein badain*. They—so that's what they're saying: Moshe's true, Torah's
true, we on the other hand are liars. אמר לי *Amar lei*,
כל תלתין יומי מהדרי להו גיהנום כבשר בתוך קלחת ואמרי הכי *kol
tlati yomei mahadri lehu Gehinnom k'vasar b'toch kalachat v'amri hachi*: משה ותורתו
אמת והן בדאין *Moshe v'torato emet v'hein badain*. And you know, every
30 days, you know, I guess there's like a cycle that this
turns. Every 30 days this happens and you know, and you timed
it right. So you can hear this again in another 30 days.
Let me go just a little further, I'll try to get to
the משנה mishnah, *Mishna* again. I'm going to have to put it
on, but—דור המדבר dor hamidbar, אין להם חלק לעולם הבא chelek le-olam
haba. *Dor HaMidbar ein lahem chelek l'olam haba*. Other people do not
have a חלק לעולם הבא chelek le-olam haba, *chelek l'olam haba*, like
the generation that was in the מדבר midbar, *Midbar*. All these people.
תנו רבנן *Tanu rabbanan*: דור המדבר dor hamidbar, אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא chelek le-olam haba *Dor HaMidbar ein lahem chelek l'olam haba*, שנאמר
*shene'emar*: במדבר הזה יתמו ושם ימותו *b'midbar hazeh yitamu v'sham yamutu*. So
like we darshened this before: יתמו *yitamu* בעולם הזה *ba'olam hazeh*, ושם
ימותו *v'sham yamutu* לעולם הבא *l'olam haba*. ואומר *v'omer*: אשר נשבעתי באפי
אם יבואון אל מנוחתי *asher nishbati b'api im yevo'un el menuchati*. We're
going to say this tonight, right? אשר נשבעתי באפי *Asher nishbati b'api*
is קבלת שבת *Kabbalat Shabbat*. That I—I swore that they would not
go to my מנוחה *menucha*, right, you know, the eternal rest. So
דברי רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *divrei Rabbi Akiva*. רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi
Eliezer omer*: הן
באים לעולם הבא *hein ba'im l'olam haba*, שנאמר *shene'emar*: אספו לי חסידי
כורתי בריתי Isfu li chasidai koretay veriti, עלי זבח alay zavach, *isfu
li chasidai koreti
briti alei zavach*. Gather me the חסידים *chasidim*, like,
you know, those—those that enter into a covenant with me. I that
I swore? Yeah,
שנשבעתי באפי, right? So מן התרת נדרים, min hatarat nedarim, there's a
way to get you out, right? If you would have whatever done
it again and they ask you, no, I wouldn't have done it
again, I regret having done it, my causes were mistaken. So God
swore in his haste, so he got us,
באפי נשבעתי ובחרוני שבי, be-api nishbati u-vecharoni shavi, right? He did it
in haste, but then he reconsidered and then thought better of it
and said no they could have a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek le-olam
haba. יהושע בן פרחיה אומר לא נאמר פסוק זה אלא
כנגד דורות הבאים.
Yehoshua ben Perachia omer lo ne-emar pasuk zeh ella keneged
dorot haba-im. So this פסוק pasuk that we were just talking about
that רבי
אלעזר
Rabbi
Elazar said, that אספו לי חסידי Isfu li chasidai כורתי
בריתי, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says they don't get a חלק
לעולם הבא, chelek le-olam haba רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says they do
and he cited this פסוק. pasuk, But so this רב is now
saying, yeah, the פסוק pasuk. that was just cited in support of
them having a חלק לעולם הבא chelek le-olam haba. could really be
about something else, so you don't just say that they have a
חלק לעולם הבא. chelek le-olam haba. So אספו לי חסידי is not
the time of the מדבר, midbar but the צדיקים שבכל דור ודור,
tzadikim she-be-khol dor va-dor, right? It's כנגד דורות הבאים. keneged dorot haba-im.
So coming
generations, which in some ways
is nice to say that there are those in every generation, there'll
be righteous ones. And God looks out for them. כורתי בריתי עלי
זבח, Koretay veriti alay zavach, those that entered into this covenant are
not just the people of the מדבר midbar. but those are חנניה
מישאל ועזריה Chananiah Mishael va-Azariah שמסרו את עצמם לתוך כבשן האש. she-masru
et atzmam le-tokh kivshan ha-esh. So עלי זבח, אלו רבי עקיבא וחבריו
elu Rabbi Akiva ve-chaverav שמסרו עצמן לשחיטה על דברי
תורה.
she-masru atzman li-shchita al divrei
torah. Those are the people we're talking about. שמעון בן עזאי אומר
והיו להם לחלק לעולם הבא. Shimon ben Azzai omer ve-hayu lahem le-chelek
le-olam haba. So we're going back and forth, do these דור המדבר
have a חלק לעולם הבא or not. They do, he says, שנאמר
ופדויי ה' ישובון ובאו ציון ברנה. she-ne-emar u-fduyey Hashem yeshuvun u-vau tziyon
be-rina. Those are redeemed by ה', Hashem, which בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
were redeemed by ה'. Hashem. So they will come back, ציון, Tziyon,
ציון, Tziyon, we're not talking about like the ingathering of future exiles,
we're talking about the future of ציון, Tziyon, the עולם הבא. olam
haba. Obviously
you could take it many different ways.
All right.
אמר רבי יוחנן שבקיה רבי עקיבא לחסידותיה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan shevakeih Rabbi
Akiva le-chasiduteih. Usually רבי עקיבא is like the one that's more
inclusive and he would be like that, but he's the one that
said that these people, דור המדבר, don't have a חלק לעולם הבא.
So he sort of left his usual חסידות chasidut as they're referring
to this here. And he's citing a פסוק, שנאמר הלך וקראת באזני
ירושלים לאמר זכרתי לך חסד נעוריך אהבת
כלולותיך לכתך אחרי במדבר בארץ לא זרועה. she-ne-emar halokh ve-karata be-oznei yerushalayim
lemor zacharti lakh chesed neurayikh ahavat kelulotayikh lekhtekh acharai bamidbar be-eretz lo
zeruah. Remember your the old kindness in your the days of your
youth, meaning בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael when they're young and a new
nation of God. How they followed me in the מדבר. So
we call on זכות אבות zechut avot all the time, that's in
the פסוק. הבן יקיר לי אפרים, Haben yakir li Efrayim, that whole
thing. God is saying, I'm redeeming because I remember the righteousness of
the people from long ago.
So if we call on their זכות, zechut, God remembers it, הינו
הם לא כל שכן? hinno hem lo kol sheken? Don't they have
enough of their own זכות zechut to be entering עולם הבא? olam
haba? So he thinks that they do have a חלק לעולם הבא.
So this משנה, mishnah at least this part of the משנה about
the דור המדבר, is not necessarily agreed upon by everybody. So let's
stop here.
יישר כח. Yasher koach. Thank you. Who's doing tomorrow?
I think Dan is. Okay.